Inventory of the Robert G. Wesson papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Robert G. Wesson papers
1936-1991
81073
Hoover Institution Archives
18 manuscript boxes (7 linear feet)
Correspondence, writings, memoranda, and clippings relating to the Soviet political system, political and economic conditions in Latin America and other parts of the world, and the theory of evolution.
Wesson, Robert G.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1981.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
Robert G. Wesson was an American political scientist who served as a senior research fellow at the Hoover Institution for over a decade. Wesson was interested in natural science and philosophy as well as political science, and as a result, his works, numbering over 30 published books in his career, span topics ranging from debt in Latin America to modern thought on the theory of evolution. Born in Washington D.C. in 1920, Wesson served in the Navy between 1944 and 1946. Wesson served with the Foreign Service in Brazil and Columbia and spent a number of years living in South America. He received his bachelor's degree at the University of Arizona, his master's at Tufts University's Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy, and his Ph.D. in political science at Columbia University. He taught for thirteen years at the University of California at Santa Barbara before joining the Hoover Institution in 1977. He had eight children and died of cancer in 1991 at 71 years of age.
Sources:
http://www.nytimes.com/1991/07/03/obituaries/robert-g-wesson-71-expert-on-soviet-union.html
http://news.stanford.edu/pr/91/910702Arc1265.html
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers are comprised of correspondence, writings, memoranda, and clippings relating to the Soviet political system, political and economic conditions in Latin America and other parts of the world, and the theory of evolution.
The papers primarily document Wesson's work as a senior research fellow at the Hoover Institution from 1978 to his death in 1991. A prolific writer, his many articles and essays on politics and economy in Latin America, communism, international relations, and democracy are included in the collection.
Wesson worked on a number of projects and events, including the Hoover Institution publication series "Politics in Latin America" and a conference on Latin American debt. Articles and correspondence related to these and other projects are included in the Correspondence and Writings by Others series.
Evolution.; Latin America--Economic conditions--1945-; Latin America--Politics and government--20th century.; Soviet Union--Politics and government.; World politics--1945-1989.
- Clippings of articles by or about Wesson, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 1: 1)
- Clippings of articles by or about Wesson, 1981-1983 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  Scope and Contents note
  Increment of November 1984
- General correspondence and memoranda, 1985-1990
  - 1985 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - 1986 (Box-folder 1: 4-5)
  - 1987 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - 1988 (Box-folder 2: 1-2)
  - 1989 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - 1990 (Box-folder 2: 4-5)
- T.P.S. (Teaching Political Science), notes and correspondance on the publication, 1981-1985 (Box-folder 2: 6)
- Kirkpatrick, Mark and Russell Lande. "The Evolution of Maternal Characters" Evolution, 43 (3), 1989, pp. 485-503 (Box-folder 2: 7)
- Correspondence and Writings by Others, 1979-1991
  Includes articles and essays by colleagues of Wesson and related correspondence. Arranged alphabetically by author
  - Adams, Richard, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - Alexander, Richard, 1990 (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - Allen, Garland, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 2: 10)
  - Amaral, Samuel, 1987 (Box-folder 2: 11)
  - Anderson, Tom, 1981-1989 (Box-folder 2: 12-13)
  - Baer, Werner, 1982-1984 (Box-folder 2: 14)
  - Bagley, Bruce, 1984 (Box-folder 2: 15)
  - Barash, David, 1990 (Box-folder 2: 16)
  - Bickerton, Derek, 1991 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - Bigler, Gene, 1981-1986 (Box-folder 3: 2)
  - Blank, David, 1979-1985 (Box-folder 3: 3)
  - Booth, John, 1982-1985 (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - Boyer, Howard, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 3: 5)
  - Breck, Henry, 1987 (Box-folder 3: 6)
  - Brossard, E. B., 1986 (Box-folder 3: 7)
  - Burress, Richard, 1982-1988 (Box-folder 3: 8)
  - Camp, Roderic Ai, 1986 (Box-folder 3: 9)
  - Campbell, Bernard, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 3: 10)
  - Campbell, John, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 3: 11)
  - Cavarozzi, Marcelo, 1984-1984 (Box-folder 3: 12)
  - Cela-Conde, Camilo J., 1990-1991 (Box-folder 3: 13)
  - El Centro de Estudios de la Realidad Economica y Social (CERES), 1986 (Box-folder 3: 14)
  - Child, Jack, 1982-1985 (Box-folder 3: 15)
  - Colome, Rinaldo, circa 1987 (Box-folder 3: 16)
  - Denton, Michael, 1990 (Box-folder 3: 17)
  - Dix, Robert, 1984-1986 (Box-folder 3: 18)
  - Dominguez, Jorge, 1984-1986 (Box-folder 3: 19)
  - Dover, Gabriel, 1988-1990 (Box-folder 3: 20)
  - Duncan, W. Raymond, 1980-1983 (Box-folder 3: 21)
  - Durham, Bill, 1991 (Box-folder 3: 22)
  - Dyke, Charles, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 3: 23)
  - Eibl-Eibesfeldt, I., 1990-1991 (Box-folder 3: 24)
  - Falcoff, Mark, 1982-1986 (Box-folder 3: 25)
  - Fishlow, Albert, 1982-1987 (Box-folder 3: 26)
  - Fitch, John, 1987 (Box-folder 3: 27)
  - Fleischer, David V., 1981-1988 (Box-folder 3: 28-29)
  - Flew, Antony, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - Fontaine, Arturo, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 4: 2)
  - Garcia, Jose, 1984-1987 (Box-folder 4: 3)
  - Garcia Passalacqua, Juan M., 1982-1984 (Box-folder 4: 4)
  - Gallanter, Sanford, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - Gewirth, Alan, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 4: 6)
  - Gillespie, Charles, 1987-1989 (Box-folder 4: 7)
  - Glade, William, 1982-1987 (Box-folder 4: 8)
  - Godfrey, Laurie, 1990 (Box-folder 4: 9)
  - Goodwin, Brian, 1990 (Box-folder 4: 10)
  - Grabendorff, Wolf, 1983-1986 (Box-folder 4: 11)
  - Graham, Lawrence, 1985-1988 (Box-folder 4: 12)
  - Gray, Anthony, 1982-1985 (Box-folder 4: 13)
  - Gunther, Richard, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 4: 14)
  - Henriksen, Thomas, 1983-1990 (Box-folder 4: 15)
  - Herrnstein, Richard, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 4: 16-17)
  - Hilton, Ronald, 1986-1988 (Box-folder 4: 18)
  - Horton, Karen, 1988-1989 (Box-folder 4: 19)
  - Huber, John, 1991 (Box-folder 4: 20)
  - Jerison, Harry, 1989-1991 (Box-folder 4: 21)
  - Jones, Peter, 1985 (Box-folder 4: 22)
  - Kavanaugh, Dennis, 1985-1987 (Box-folder 4: 23)
  - Kaye, Howard, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 4: 24)
  - Keithley, John, 1991 (Box-folder 5: 1)
  - Lieberman, Philip, 1991 (Box-folder 5: 2)
  - Lieuwen, Edwin, 1981 (Box-folder 5: 3)
  - Lijphart, Arend, 1987 (Box-folder 5: 4)
  - Livingstone, James, 1987 (Box-folder 5: 5)
  - Lloyd, Elisabeth, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 5: 6)
  - Lowenthal, Abraham F., 1983-1988 (Box-folder 5: 7)
  - Lupsha, Peter, 1985-1989 (Box-folder 5: 8)
  - Mackle, George, 1991 (Box-folder 5: 9)
  - Makeig, Douglas, 1985-1987 (Box-folder 5: 10)
  - Markl, Hubert, 1990 (Box-folder 5: 11)
  - Marini, John, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 5: 12-13)
  - Martz, John, 1981-1990 (Box-folder 5: 14)
  - Matsushita, Hiroshi, 1984-1988 (Box-folder 5: 15)
  - McEvoy, Paul, 1991 (Box-folder 5: 16)
  - Merkx, Gilbert, 1988 (Box-folder 5: 17)
  - Miklos, George, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 5: 18)
  - Millett, Richard, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 5: 19)
  - Moneta, Carlos, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 5: 20)
  - Moore, John, 1981-1985 (Box-folder 5: 21)
  - Mortlock, Robert P., 1988 (Box-folder 6: 1)
  - Muñoz, Heraldo, 1982-1986 (Box-folder 6: 2)
  - Needler, Martin C., 1980-1989 (Box-folder 6: 3)
  - Niksch, Larry, 1986-1988 (Box-folder 6: 4)
  - Nuccio, Richard, 1985-1988 (Box-folder 6: 5)
  - Olsen, Edward, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 6: 6)
  - On the Politics in Latin America Monograph Series, 1980-1985 (Box-folder 6: 7)
  - Palmer, David Scott, 1980-1985 (Box-folder 6: 8)
  - Pastoriza, Tomas, 1986-1988 (Box-folder 6: 9)
  - Pearson, Neal, 1981-1983 (Box-folder 6: 10)
  - Perry, Glenn E., 1985-1988 (Box-folder 6: 11)
  - Plattner, Marc, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 6: 12)
  - Powell, David, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 6: 13)
  - Pratt, Joe D., 1990 (Box-folder 6: 14)
  - Purcell, Susan, 1987 (Box-folder 6: 15)
  - Puyana, Alicia, 1988-1989 (Box-folder 6: 16)
  - Rabkin, Roda, 1984-1990 (Box-folder 6: 17)
  - Radnitzky, Gerard, 1989-1990 (Box-folder 6: 18)
  - Raisian, John, 1988-1991 (Box-folder 6: 19-20)
  - Ratliff, William, 1983-1988 (Box-folder 6: 21)
  - Roberts, Paul, 1987 (Box-folder 7: 1)
  - Rockman, Bert, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 7: 2)
  - Romero, Anibal, 1986-1989 (Box-folder 7: 3)
  - Ropp, Steve, 1981-1986 (Box-folder 7: 4)
  - Rosenberg, Mark, 1987-1989 (Box-folder 7: 5)
  - Rubinstein, Alvin, 1982-1985 (Box-folder 7: 6)
  - Rudolph, James, 1983-1991 (Box-folder 7: 7)
  - Sagan, Dorion and Lynn Margulis, 1990 (Box-folder 7: 8)
  - Schurmann, Franz, 1985 (Box-folder 7: 9)
  - Segal, Aaron, 1987 (Box-folder 7: 10)
  - Sigmund, Paul, 1988 (Box-folder 7: 11)
  - Singh, Chaitram, 1984-1987 (Box-folder 7: 12)
  - Sloan, John, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 7: 13)
  - Slobodkin, L. B., 1990-1991 (Box-folder 7: 14)
  - Smocovitis, Betty, 1990 (Box-folder 7: 15)
  - Snow, Peter, 1981-1982 (Box-folder 7: 16)
  - Sober, Elliott, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 7: 17)
  - The Spitzer Foundation, 1985 (Box-folder 7: 18)
  - Staar, Richard, 1981-1988 (Box-folder 7: 19)
  - Stanton, Betty, 1991 (Box-folder 7: 20)
  - Steiner, John, 1990 (Box-folder 7: 21)
  - Stone, Carl, 1983-1985 (Box-folder 7: 22)
  - Story, Dale, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 7: 23)
  - Suchlicki, Jaime, 1981-1985 (Box-folder 8: 1)
  - Swenson, Rod, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 8: 2-3)
  - Taylor, Philip, 1985-1987 (Box-folder 8: 4)
  - Thompson, Stuart, 1990 (Box-folder 8: 5)
  - Triska, Jan F., 1985-1987 (Box-folder 8: 6)
  - Trejo, Saul, 1987 (Box-folder 8: 7)
  - Urcuyo, Constantino, 1987 (Box-folder 8: 8)
  - Valdez, Nelson, 1980-1985 (Box-folder 8: 9)
  - Valenta, Jiri, 1982-1986 (Box-folder 8: 10)
  - Valenzuela, Arturo, 1983-1985 (Box-folder 8: 11)
  - Wager, Stephen J., 1983-1986 (Box-folder 8: 12)
  - Waisman, Carlos, 1987 (Box-folder 8: 13)
  - Watkins, Albert, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 8: 14)
  - Weber, Bruce, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 8: 15-16)
  - Wenegrat, Brant, 1991 (Box-folder 8: 17-18)
  - Wilson, Edward O., 1990 (Box-folder 8: 19)
  - Wright, Richard, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 8: 20)
  - Wynia, Gary, 1982-1987 (Box-folder 8: 21)
  - Zihlman, 1991 (Box-folder 8: 22)
- Correspondence on publications, 1969-1991
  Includes correspondence with publishers and colleagues, royalty statements, editing notes, and clippings. Arranged alphabetically by publication
  - The Aging of Communism, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 9: 1)
  - The American Problem, undated (Box-folder 9: 2)
  - Beyond Natural Selection, 1989-1990 (Box-folder 9: 3-5)
  - Brazil in Transition, 1982-1983 (Box-folder 9: 6)
  - Brown, Betsy, 1983 (Box-folder 9: 7)
  - Butterfield Publishing, 1989 (Box-folder 9: 8)
  - Communism and Communist Systems, 1977-1987 (Box-folder 9: 9)
  - Coping with the Latin American Debt, 1987-1990 (Box-folder 9: 10)
  - The Cosmic Symphony, 1991 (Box-folder 9: 11)
  - Cosmos and Metacosmos, 1989-1990 (Box-folder 9: 12-16)
  - Democracy, 1985-1988 (Box-folder 9: 17)
  - Democracy: World Survey 1987, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 9: 18-22)
  - Democracy in Latin America: Promise and Problems, 1980-1983 (Box-folder 10: 1)
  - Evolution, 1991 (Box-folder 10: 2)
  - Evolution of Intelligence, 1991 (Box-folder 10: 3-4)
  - Evolutionary Theory and Human Values and/or Darwinism and Society, 1989-1990 (Box-folder 10: 5)
  - Foreign Policy for a New Age, 1975-1984 (Box-folder 10: 6)
  - German Version of The Problem of Soviet Foreign Policy, 1969-1981 (Box-folder 10: 7)
  - International Relations, 1988-1989 (Box-folder 10: 8)
  - Jensen, Kirk, 1991 (Box-folder 7: 9)
  - The Latin American Military Institution, 1982-1989 (Box-folder 10: 10)
  - Latin American Views of U.S. Foreign Policy, 1982-1986 (Box-folder 10: 11)
  - Lenin's Legacy, 1974-1984 (Box-folder 10: 12)
  - Prentice Hall on Publishing Modern Governements, 1980-1987 (Box-folder 10: 13)
  - Monographs, 1984-1988 (Box-folder 10: 14)
  - Prentice Hall on Publishing Politics: Individual and State, 1986-1988 (Box-folder 11: 1)
  - Praeger Publishers, 1986-1988 (Box-folder 11: 2)
  - Politics, Policies, and Economic Development in Latin America, 1981-1986 (Box-folder 11: 3)
  - The Problem of Soviet Foreign Policy, 1969-1985 (Box-folder 11: 4)
  - Quasidemocracy (Box-folder 11: 5)
  - The Russian Dilemma, 1975-1986 (Box-folder 11: 6)
  - Soviet Foreign Policy in Perspective, 1969-1985 (Box-folder 11: 7)
  - Soviet Union: Looking to the 1980's, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 11: 8)
  - State Systems: International Pluralism, Politics, and Culture, 1976-1984 (Box-folder 11: 9)
  - U.S. Influence in Latin America, 1980-1983 (Box-folder 11: 10)
  - Why Marxism?, 1975-1986 (Box-folder 11: 11)
- Family correspondence to Costa Rica, 1980-1991 (Box-folder 11: 12)
- Hoover Administrative Officers, general correspondence, 1985-1990 (Box-folder 11: 13)
- Miscellaneous correspondence and manuscripts, 1978-1982 (Box-folder 12: 1)
- Correspondence on The Society for Scientific Exploration, 1991 (Box-folder 12: 2)
- Correspondence on international scholars, 1986-1989 (Box-folder 12: 3)
- Correspondence to Senator Carlos Enrique Melgar of Peru, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 12: 4)
- General correspondence, 1985 (Box-folder 12: 5)
- Correspondence on debt, 1984-1986 (Box-folder 12: 6)
- Correspondence on Latin American debt conferences, 1987 (Box-folder 12: 7)
- Correspondence about articles by Wesson, 1978-1982 (Box-folder 12: 8)
- Clippings on world politics and economy, 1979-1991
  - Afghanistan, 1985 (Box-folder 12: 9)
  - Africa, 1985-1987 (Box-folder 12: 10)
  - Albania, 1985 (Box-folder 12: 11)
  - Algeria, 1979-1985 (Box-folder 12: 12)
  - Angola, 1985 (Box-folder 12: 13)
  - Bolivia, 1985-1987 (Box-folder 12: 14)
  - Brazil, 1985-1989 (Box-folder 12: 15)
  - Britain, 1985-1987 (Box-folder 12: 16)
  - Bulgaria, 1985 (Box-folder 12: 17)
  - Cambodia, 1985 (Box-folder 12: 18)
  - Columbia, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 12: 19)
  - Chile, 1985-1987 (Box-folder 12: 20)
  - China, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 13: 1)
  - Czechoslovakia, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 13: 2)
  - Eastern Europe, 1987 (Box-folder 13: 3)
  - East Germany, 1985 (Box-folder 13: 4)
  - Egypt, 1986 (Box-folder 13: 5)
  - France, 1985-1988 (Box-folder 13: 6)
  - Germany, 1985-1987 (Box-folder 13: 7)
  - Greece, 1985-1987 (Box-folder 13: 8)
  - Hungary, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 13: 9)
  - India, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 13: 10)
  - Indonesia, 1986 (Box-folder 13: 11)
  - Iran, 1986-1988 (Box-folder 13: 12)
  - Israel, 1985 (Box-folder 13: 13)
  - Italy, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 13: 14)
  - Japan, 1985-1987 (Box-folder 13: 15-16)
  - Korea, 1985-1987 (Box-folder 13: 17)
  - Latin America, 1985 (Box-folder 13: 18 - 19)
  - Lebanon, 1985 (Box-folder 13: 20)
  - Libya, 1986 (Box-folder 13: 21)
  - Malaysia, 1986 (Box-folder 13: 22)
  - Miscellaneous, circa 1984-1987 (Box-folder 13: 23)
  - Nigeria, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 13: 24)
  - North America, 1987 (Box-folder 13: 25)
  - Pakistan, 1986 (Box-folder 13: 26)
  - Philippines, 1987 (Box-folder 13: 27)
  - Poland, 1985-1987 (Box-folder 13: 28-29)
  - Portugal, 1986 (Box-folder 13: 30)
  - Romania, 1985-1987 (Box-folder 13: 31)
  - Senegal, 1987 (Box-folder 13: 32)
  - Singapore, 1986 (Box-folder 13: 33)
  - Spain, 1985 (Box-folder 13: 34)
  - Soviet Russia, 1985 (Box-folder 13: 35)
  - Sri Lanka, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 14: 1-2)
  - Sweden, 1985 (Box-folder 14: 3)
  - Switzerland, 1985 (Box-folder 14: 4)
  - Taiwan, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 14: 5)
  - Thailand, 1986 (Box-folder 14: 6)
  - The Third World, 1986 (Box-folder 14: 7)
  - Vietnam, 1985 (Box-folder 14: 8)
  - Yugoslavia, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 14: 9)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Clippings of articles by Wesson, 1991 (Box-folder 14: 10)
    - Clippings on world debt, 1987 (Box-folder 14: 11)
      Relates mainly to Latin America
    - General, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 14: 12)
    - General clippings and essays on Latin America, 1987-1990 (Box-folder 14: 13)
- Statement from Collier, 1986 (Box-folder 14: 14)
- Book reviews, 1980-1981 (Box-folder 14: 15)
- Stanford Program in Values, Technology, Science, and Society, 1988-1990 (Box-folder 14: 16)
- Essays on biology by Mea-Wan Ho, undated (Box-folder 14: 17)
- International Society for the Systems Sciences. General Systems bulletin at Cal Poly Pomona, 1990 (Box-folder 14: 18)
- Writings
  - Irrationality notes and incomplete draft, undated (Box-folder 14: 19)
  - Early writings, poetry, and notebooks, 1934-1957 (Box-folder 14: 20-21)
    Includes photographs and correspondence
  - "The Amorality of Darwinism,", undated (Box-folder 14: 22)
- Directories, addresses, and phone numbers, undated (Box-folder 14: 23)
- Obituary notices, 1991 (Box-folder 14: 24)
- Bibliography, 1987-1990 (Box-folder 14: 24)
- Visiting scholar applications, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 15: 1)
- Letter from Cecilia Rodriguez, 1991 (Box-folder 15: 2)
- Letters from Marta Weeks, 1990 (Box-folder 15: 3)
- International Studies Program, 1987 (Box-folder 15: 4)
- Hoover Institution Latin American Program, 1988 (Box-folder 15: 5)
- Biographical information on international visitors, 1985-1989 (Box-folder 15: 6)
- Reports and information on the Program in Democracy in Developing Countries, 1987-1990 (Box-folder 15: 7)
- Personal correspondence, 1978-1990 (Box-folder 15: 8)
- Biosystematists council members, 1990 (Box-folder 15: 9)
- Articles and essays on debt, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 15: 10)
- Conference papers on Latin American debt, 1987 (Box-folder 15: 11)
- Political commentary on the Middle East, 1990 (Box-folder 15: 12)
- Writings, 1978-1990
  Includes clippings of articles by Wesson
  - On third world militarism, 1990 (Box-folder 15: 13)
  - On Latin American debt, 1985-1987 (Box-folder 15: 14)
  - 1978 (Box-folder 16: 1)
  - 1979 (Box-folder 16: 2)
  - 1980 (Box-folder 16: 3)
  - 1981 (Box-folder 16: 4)
  - 1983 (Box-folder 16: 5)
  - 1984 (Box-folder 16: 6)
  - 1985 (Box-folder 16: 7)
  - 1986 (Box-folder 16: 8)
  - 1986 (contd.) (Box-folder 17: 1-2)
  - 1987 (Box-folder 17: 3-5)
  - 1988 (Box-folder 17: 6-7)
  - 1989 (Box-folder 18: 1)
  - 1990 (Box-folder 18: 2)